<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles exhibited to the Honourable House of Commons assembled in Parliament, against the Lord Inchiquine Lord president of Munster, subscribed by the Lord Broghill and Sir Arthur Loftus Knight. Together with a full and cleare answer their unto made whereby it appeares that the said articles are false scandalous and full of groundlesse aspersions. Subscribed by Rich. Gething Secretary to the said Lord President.</title>
            <author>Inchiquin, Murrough O'Brien, Earl of, 1614-1674.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75644</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3824</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E402_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201828</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862319</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862319</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114473</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75644)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114473)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 64:E402[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles exhibited to the Honourable House of Commons assembled in Parliament, against the Lord Inchiquine Lord president of Munster, subscribed by the Lord Broghill and Sir Arthur Loftus Knight. Together with a full and cleare answer their unto made whereby it appeares that the said articles are false scandalous and full of groundlesse aspersions. Subscribed by Rich. Gething Secretary to the said Lord President.</title>
                  <author>Inchiquin, Murrough O'Brien, Earl of, 1614-1674.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 2, 10 [i.e. 16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Hu. Tuckey, at the Black Spread Eagle in Fleet-Street, over against St. Dunstons Church.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>P.16 misnumbered 10.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 18th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Inchiquin, Murrough O'Brien, --  Earl of, 1614-1674.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Munster (Ireland) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114473:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ARTICLES EXHIBITED TO The Honourable Houſe of COMMONS Aſſembled In PARLIAMENT, Againſt the Lord <hi>Inchiquine</hi> Lord Preſident of <hi>Munſter,</hi> Subſcribed by the Lord <hi>Broghill</hi> and Sir <hi>Arthur Loftus</hi> Knight.</p>
            <p>Together with a full and cleare anſwer their unto made whereby it appeares that the ſaid Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles are falſe ſcandalous and full of groundleſſe aſperſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Subſcribed by</hi> Rich. Gething <hi>Secretary to the ſaid Lord Preſident.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Hu. Tuckey,</hi> at the Black Spread Eagle in Fleet-Street, over againſt St. <hi>Dunſtons</hi> Church. 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:114473:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114473:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing imployed by the Lord Preſident of <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> into <hi>England</hi> in <hi>June</hi> laſt to negotiate ſome affairs for that diſtreſsed Province I took notice that there were certain Articles preſented againſt his Lordſhip to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſe of Commons, and ſubſcribed by the Lord of <hi>Broghill</hi> and Sir <hi>Arthur Loftus</hi> Knight, and delivered to the ſpeaker of the Houſe of Commons, and meeting with a copie thereof, which I heare came from a perſon relating to the informing parties or one of them, who (probably) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned the publication thereof to aggravate thereby thoſe aſpertions againſt his Lordſhip, and to render him and his honour more publickly culpable. I have taken upon me, being well acquainted with the particulars contained in that charge by reaſon of mine attendance on his Lordſhip and the tranſaction of much of his buſineſse to compoſe a full anſwer thereunto, and to publiſh the ſame, which was forborn till now, in expectation that the Honorable Houſe of Commons would have long ere this have had ſome leiſure and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to heare and examine the ſaid Lord Preſidents vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to thoſe Artcles, unto which purpoſe they have been ſeverall times moved, but by the interpoſition of more weighty affairs his Lordſhip <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould not arrive to that degree of happineſse, by meanes whereof he hath lain ſtill under the
<pb facs="tcp:114473:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſcandall of them ſo much to his prejudice as that the Army under the command of his Excellency Sir <hi>Thomas Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax</hi> have (upon miſinformation of ſome particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons well known for by reſpects to beare cauſeleſse ill will to the ſaid Lord Preſident taken cogniſance of that accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and made uſe of it againſt ſome of the impeached members within making his Lordſhip, a party thereunto, to his Lordſhips very great diſhonour and diſadvantage, and therefore the duty and affection I ow to truth and to his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that I might endevour to undeceive all ſuch as have bin herein miſguided in their thoughts, I have been induced to vindicate his Lordſhip in this kind, which being vented with judgement and impartiality wil undoubtedly argue the informers egregiouſly and malitiouſly miſtaken (Ile ſay no more) in their objections, and his Lordſhip evidently inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent of theſe pretended crimes.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Richard Gething. Secretary to the Lord Preſident.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:114473:3"/>
            <head>Articles humbly preſented to the Honourable Houſe of Commons aſſembled in Parliament againſt Murrogh. Brion L. Baron of <hi>Inchequin</hi> and Lord Preſident of <hi>Munſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Cuſtodiums which by his Lordſhips in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions ſhould have been imployed to the Publick uſe or for the reward of well deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Officers have been conferred upon Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers that actually ſerved againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in <hi>England,</hi> and upon his own me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall Servants, as Barbers, grooms, &amp;c. who have thereby been inabled to live in plenty, when many others of good merrit have been in exceeding great want.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That his Lordſhip hath placed ſo many Officers that have actually ſerved againſt the Parliament in <hi>England,</hi> in commands in the Parliaments Army in <hi>Munſter,</hi> that upon a rumour of the Earle of <hi>Ormonds</hi> coming down with an Army againſt that Province, it was thought fit to adminiſter an Oath to all Officers and Souldiers of the Army that might oblige them to be faithfull to the Parliament which was laid aſide upon Conſideration that the Cavaliers were ſo numerous in the Army, that their refuſall of it might endanger the loſſe of the Province.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That one <hi>Charles Honeſey</hi> an Iriſh Papiſt, who in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Rebellion ſerved as a Lieutenant of Horſe on the Parliaments ſide, and afterwards went to the Rebells, where he
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114473:4"/>actually ſerved againſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and in the ceſſation ſurpriſed a conſiderable Calile in the Parliaments quarters in <hi>Munſter</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Barries</hi> Court, and in proceſſe of time became a Collouell of the Rebells, and Lieutenant of their Ordnance, afterwards had a protection given him by the Lord Preſident (his Regiment then in being) contrary to the advice of ſome of the Councell of, ſome of the Province who was conſulted with about it.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That one <hi>Piers Perri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er</hi> who had robbed many Engliſh, and that had been at the beſieging, taking, and pillaging of many Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh mens Caſtles where he expreſt much barbarouſneſſe to the Engliſh, and who had and yet hath two ſons Officers in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells Army who were at the beſieging of <hi>Tonghall,</hi> yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſaid <hi>Ferriter</hi> had a protection from his Lordſhip though he lived in ſo remote a part of the Country, as that we could not probably derive any advantage by in and which he made uſe of to the Parliaments ſhips that touched upon that coaſt as he gained from them Ordnance and Mun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> which we are credibly informed he afterwards employed againſt the Engliſh, and notwithſtanding all this his protection ſtands ſtill in force.</p>
            <p n="5">5 That one <hi>Dominick Ferriter</hi> ſon to the ſaid <hi>P. Ferriter</hi> being brought to <hi>Cork</hi> by Admirall <hi>Moulton,</hi> as in hoſtage for the ſaid <hi>Pierce</hi> his delivering up a conſiderable Iſland in the Weſt, then and now in his poſſeſſion to the Parliaments forces upon demand the ſaid <hi>Dominick</hi> was ſet at liberty by the Lord of <hi>Inchequin</hi> upon 500 <abbr>l.</abbr> Bond of one <hi>Croſby</hi> and <hi>Fites Morris</hi> two Iriſh men, the latter alſo having ſerved againſt the Parliament in <hi>England,</hi> and yet had foot companies given them, by his Lordſhip, ſince <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, the ſaid two Captains being as his Lordſhip well knew) not worth ſo many ſhillings, the ſaid <hi>Dominick</hi> being out upon their bai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fled to the Rebells, and hath ſince raiſed a foot company to ſerve againſt the Proteſtants, but the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d two Captains were not queſtioned untill after the arrivall of ſome of the new Collonels which was about <hi>February</hi> laſt, though the ſaid <hi>Ferritor</hi> was fled long before.</p>
            <p n="6">6 That one <hi>Lombard</hi> living at <hi>Limrick</hi> in the Rebells quarters had his Rent duly taken up for him in the city of <hi>Cork</hi> by one
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114473:4"/>
               <hi>Punch</hi> an Iriſh Papiſt (ſince dead) being authorized thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by a Warrant from the ſaid Lord Preſident and that ſince the laid <hi>Punch</hi> his death one <hi>Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>pere Steward</hi> to the Lord <hi>Inchiquine</hi> was authorized by the ſaid <hi>Lambert</hi> by Letter of Atturney to continue the receiving of the ſaid Rents.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That one <hi>Fitz Patricke</hi> a notorious Rebeil and of very neere kin to the Lord Preſident was admitted into the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of <hi>Corke</hi> to treat with him to the great diſhartening of the well affected Engliſh, And that ſuddenly after the ſaid <hi>Fitz Patricke</hi> being there, his Lordſhip employed one Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Alexander Piget</hi> a confident of his owne) unto <hi>Dublin</hi> upon pretence of carrying Letters to the Parliaments Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners then ſent to treat with the Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond,</hi> but delivered them no Meſſage or Letter, though he met them at the Harbours mouth (returning after the treaty was broke off) yet went he then into <hi>Dublin,</hi> and continued there about a fort night for which he was never queſtioned.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That upon a diſcourſe betwixt his Lordſhip and one Collonel <hi>Pollard</hi> about the King, and his Lordſhip delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up the Garriſons of that Province to the Parliament, his Lordſhip ſaid theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi> If the King had dealt by me as he might have done, things had not beene here as now they are.</p>
            <p n="9">9. That their hath beene great abuſes in the ſtores of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctualls by his Lordſhip.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That there hath beene divers Prieſts Souldiers in Command, ſome of the Rebells ſupreame Councell, and ſome of their generall Aſſembly protected by his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That publique Maſſe hath beene frequently ſaid in <hi>Corke</hi> and in <hi>Kinſale</hi> ſince his Lordſhip being made of the Province by the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That his Lordſhip going to beſiege a Caſtle called <hi>Ballimartire</hi> belonging to one <hi>Edmund Fitz Gerrald</hi> (a noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious bloudy Rebell and his Lordſhips Uncle) gave order to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114473:5"/>an Officer of the Army to goe into the Caſtle, and there to ſignify to the Prieſts and Religious men that his Lordſhip was content they ſhould have free liberty to bee, Provided they went away before the Gunnes were planted, which Sir <hi>Arthur Loftus</hi> having told his Lordſhip that if the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould know of ſuch actions that they would deſert us, Whereupon the Meſſage was forborne.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>We whoſe names are ſubſcribed doe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to have all theſe above mentioned Articles ſufficiently proved.</hi>
Broghill Arthur Loftus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="reply_to_articles">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:114473:5"/>
            <head>The anſwer to the ſaid Articles.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>To the Firſt.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat Cuſtodiums according to the Lord Preſidents Inſtructions were imployed to the publique uſe, or for reward of well deſerving Officers, and for the content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Officers generally when meanes was ſhort, or rather when there was no meanes at all ſtirring and for the incouragement of ſuch as did both raiſe and reinforce their Troopes and Companies at their owne coſts and charge, and by their owne Induſtry without having any advance from the State. That no Cuſtodium hath been conferred, on any Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer that hath ſerved under the King untill he had actually ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Parliament, nor upon his meniall Servants, but ſuch as were Members of the Army, or where the Proprieter had made over ſome precedent intereſt or ingagement unto them, upon the expelling the Iriſh out of <hi>Corke,</hi> and other Garriſons it was of good advantage to the State, That his Lordſhip ſhould place any perſons in the ſeverall Meſſuages and Tenements in the Townes and Lands in the Country on condition to repaire and uphold the houſing, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe being waſt and uninhabited would have fallen to the ground and to incourage tillage about the Garriſons or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe the Lands would have layen waſt and the Souldiers have wanted quarters to lodge in both in Towne and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, neither were they then of any yearely value, and if the Lord Preſident had not ſo granted them, they were no Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants or under takers that were able to ſtocke or manure them, or to give any conſiderable Rent out of them which yet the Officers did pay to the publique by Takes, Rates and impoſitions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> layd as occaſion and the neceſſity of the Army required. And the Lord Preſident hath beene induced to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer houſes to ſeverall perſons on condition only to keepe them
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114473:6"/>up, with promiſe that if they were not allowed to hold them a conſiderable time, they ſhould be reimburſed their charges and though by that meanes many of the bonies were preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, yet for want of Inhabitants, and more ſuch undertakers about 3000. good houſes in <hi>Corke,</hi> and neere as many in <hi>Yog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall</hi> have beene demoliſhed by the Souldiers finding them empty, and for want of fireing on their guards, and in caſe the Lord Preſident wanting meanes to maintaine his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, had aſſigned them Cuſtodiums or ſome profit out of their eſtates, which by his induſtry were ſubject to Cuſtodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums it is conceived to be without prejudice, and to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the publike ſervice, his Lordſhip having taken care that an exact accompt upon oath ſhould be kept of all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of Cuſtodiums to the end the State might be anſwered for the ſame out of the pay of the Officers or otherwiſe, and if the profits and values of thoſe Cuſtodiums granted to his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall Servants as Grooms and Barbers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Who are not Officers of the Army were computed, they would not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount unto 40.<abbr>l.</abbr> 
                  <hi>per annum</hi> at that time, and the ſame may be charged on the Lord Preſidents accompt, and ſo no diſſervice to the State can ariſe, As for the imputation that his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants lived in greater plenty then others of their quality, it is but a bitter inſinnuation, or if they did live ſo, it was by their owne induſtry, and if others of better merrit were in want 40. <abbr>l.</abbr> 
                  <hi>per annum</hi> would have afforded them but little releife, and it was ſo little the Lord Preſidents deſire the States Intereſt ſhould want improvement. That he hath often importuned and deſired by his ſeverall addreſſes hither to the Houſe, and to the ſeverall Committees, that a Committee might be ſent over for the ſetling and taking of accompts of Cuſtodiums and for leaſing out Houſes and Lands for ſome ſuch terme as might induce Tenants to give a certaine Rent after the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers had improved them and drawne in Tenants upon them, and ſuch a Committee his Lordſhip was promiſed, and an Order was made for ſending them away in <hi>September</hi> 1645. which occaſioned that his Lordſhip in expectation of them did nothing of himſelfe in order to the recalling of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodiums, And further aſſoone as the Lord Preſident did ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive the Commiſſioners appointed long before, did deliver
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114473:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>in a Booke at the Councell table of the Cuſtodiums, their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues according to their returnes made unto them upon oath, of which Cuſtodiums divers were granted by the Lord <hi>Brog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill</hi> during the Lord Preſidents being in <hi>England</hi> his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip having then left him his Vice Preſident.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>To the ſecond.</head>
               <p n="2">2. That many Officers who had ſerved againſt the Parliament in <hi>England</hi> were placed in Commands there is true, And it is as true, and well knowne to the Lord of <hi>Broghill</hi> and Sir <hi>Arthur Loftus</hi> that the moſt part of them were not of his Lordſhips placeing therein, as the Regiment which upon ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render of <hi>Wareham</hi> to the Parliament, conditioned to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruited to receive a months meanes, and to be ſent for <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> and the Regiment ſent over with Sir <hi>Arthur Loftus</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting for the moſt part both Officers and Souldiers of ſuch as had ſerved the King againſt the Parliament, and were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Priſoners at <hi>Nazeby.</hi> Beſides the Officers and Souldiers that were at ſeverall times ſent over by the Parliaments Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls out of Wales, Cornewall, and other parts, and were enlarged and ſent into that ſervice, by order of the Parliament or of the Committees of the Houſe, and the Lord Preſident hath not preferred any ſuch Officers of his owne accord to Command, but ſuch as have approved themſelves faithfull, and have well deſerved there, and of whoſe fidelity to the Parliament, and cauſe he is well aſſured, and that none of them is tainted with any diſaffection though often in much want and extremity nor did any that ſerved the Parliament want preferment to his Lordſhips power. It is true, that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a report of the Lord <hi>Ormonds</hi> breaking off with the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments Commiſſioners. It fell into debate whether ſuch an Oath (as is in the Article mentioned) were not neceſſary, and it being conceived that moſt of thoſe Officers even of thoſe that had ſerved the King were ſent out of <hi>England</hi> by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and had taken the Covenant, and given teſtimony of their fidelity in that ſervice it was judged unneceſſary and pleaded againſt by the Lord <hi>Braghill</hi> with much earneſtnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap> late opinions and not upon the conſiderations in the Article mentioned. And the Lord Preſident did conceive, (and hopes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114473:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>it will be ſo eſteemed) that he did the Parliament good and acceptable ſervice upon expelling the Iriſh about 3 yeares ſince being at that time in want of Officers, to draw over ſuch Officers and perſons of quality as he had intereſt in to ſerve the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereby the Kings Army was much impaired, and the Parliaments Army againſt the Rebels ſtrengthened.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>To the third.</head>
               <p n="3">3 It may be, that one <hi>Charles Heneſey</hi> had a ſafe guard or Letpaſſe for certain ſeaſons, and for ſome ſhort time underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to lay down his Arms, and to ſubmit to contribution with the county according to the generall Articles, and that he had a protection thereupon, but if his Regiment were in being (as in the Article is mentioned) his protection was thereby forfeited and upon notice thereof (if the Relators had acquainted the Lord Preſident therewith) he would have given warrant for ſeiſing his Perſon and goods, as in like caſe was uſuall, and it is certain the Officers of the Army would have ſuddenly taken the penalty thereof, as they had in like caſes, whereby ſome have got good booty, and have made it very penall to the delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, but ſome further cauſe may be aſſigned for granting ſuch protections to him, in order to the States ſervice, if any ſuch be had, of all reaſons it can with leaſt Juſtice be imputed either to favour, or affection, or any other by reſpect, the Lord Preſident abhorring ſuch courſes he having hanged this mans brother in the market place at <hi>Cork</hi> And ſo farre was the Lord Preſident from granting this man any thing, of particular favour, as that he had often threatned to hang him where ever he could be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tached, for that very act in the Article mentioned <hi>viz.</hi> the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying and ſurpriſing of <hi>Barries</hi> court. This <hi>Heneſey</hi> being a man of ſo baſe extraction, and of ſo little eſteem with the Rebels themſelves, as that in reaſon the Lord Preſident could neither have reſpects unto him, or ends upon him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>To the fourth.</head>
               <p>That <hi>Peirce Ferriter</hi> hath ſuccoured, relieved and preſerved many of the diſtreſſed, ſtripped Engliſh at the beginning of the Rebellion and ſithence hath been ſufficiently atteſted, and is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on record, but that he ever robbed or pillaged any, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> never yet appeared to the Lord Preſident. That he was a great means of relieving the Fort of <hi>Ballingarry</hi> (a place of great importance
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114473:7"/>in the Weſt of <hi>Kerry</hi> on the Sea coaſts, and impregnable by force maintained by Captain <hi>David Crosby</hi> againſt the Rebells ſee 4 or 5 yeares at his own charge principally, untill the number of 80 men were reduced to three, is a pregnant truth. That the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſland of <hi>Blaſques</hi> which Maſter <hi>Perriter</hi> in <hi>Habiteth</hi> being a league of the Coaſt, affords great refreſhing to our ſhipping be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Sea, or anchoring about the mouth of <hi>Shanon,</hi> called the river of <hi>Limerick</hi> will be acknowledged where they have beene frequently ſupplyed, with freſh meat and water, and that the Lord Preſident did grant him a ſafeguard (intending to make uſe of him for the relief of <hi>Ballingary</hi>) deſiring the Seamen to forbeare prejudicing of him during his good deportment is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable; but if it had been made appeare, that he had committed any act of diſadvantage to any of our party ſithence that ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard. The Lord Preſident would not onely leave the ſhipping at Liberty to take revenge, but would have incited them and contributed thereunto, if he have made any advantage of the Parliaments ſhipping it is more then the Lord Preſident could foreſee, yet the Lord Preſident did deſire that he might be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with ſome neceſſaries to incourage him (though not artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery) having ſome deſigne towards theſe parts, and it appears the Seamen were cautions of letting him have any thing but on good aſſurance, for they took his ſon (as Hoſtage) for what they delivered, and if the Relators underſtood he employed the Guns or any thing he had of them againſt the Engliſh, and did not inform the Lord Preſident thereof, they were to blame and yet that he ſhould in thoſe remote parts imploy them againſt the Engliſh is improbable, there being no Engliſh Gariſon nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer him then <hi>Baltamors,</hi> or Caſtle haven about 80 miles diſtant from him, eſpecially conſidering how little friendſhip he had with the Rebells, from whom he had taken two ſhips that came under his Iſland, as manifeſtly did appeare unto the Lord Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>To the fifth.</head>
               <p>That <hi>Dominick Ferriter</hi> was brought as an Hoſtage to <hi>Cork</hi> by Admirall <hi>Moulton</hi> is apparent, but whether for delivery of an Iſland, or for reſtitution of the two ſmall Guns, and the Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition delivered to his father is doubtfull. But this being either determined or depending at a Court of War, the Relatons might
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114473:8"/>have ſpared the Honorable Houſe the trouble of debating it. That <hi>Dominick</hi> being bayled by the two Genlemen in the Article mentioned, made an eſcape is true, but that thoſe ſureties were taken by the Lord Preſidents direction, doth not appeare, you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably it might be ſo, That thoſe men offering to be bound body for body, and not being then of the Army, were accepted by his Lordſhips approbation, And where they are ſaid to be Iriſh men the one of them <hi>viz.</hi> Captain <hi>Crosby</hi> hath been alwayes bred a zealous and good Proteſtant, and the ſon of a Proteſtant, alwayes accounted an Engliſh man, and never ſerved but againſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, and the other is of Engliſh extraction (as the Relators are) and alwayes bred a Proteſtant, and admitted here to go over a Volunteere after he was taken priſoner, where he took the oath, and hath faithfully ſerved againſt the Rebells, and for the penall ſumme wherein they became bound, though it ſurpaſſe their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities at preſent, yet it may be in their power to recover or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie for the ſaid two ſmall Guns and Ammunition (the chief in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement whereon <hi>Ferriter</hi> lay at ſtake) for the doing whereof time was deſired of the Court of War. That they were not que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned ſooner after <hi>Ferriters</hi> departure was by reaſon the Lord Preſident had not information thereof till they were made Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and then his Lordſhip being made acquainteed therewith convented them before a Councell of Warre, and whether any new Collonels, who had been long a coming, were come over then or no is not materiall, and it ſeemes the buſineſſe was a while forborn in expectation that the Gentlemen might procure <hi>Ferriters</hi> return, or to procure that Gunnes for which he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged him, whereof they were confident to recover the one or the other, in reaſonable time, the judgement of <hi>Crosby</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to become bound for young <hi>Ferrtter</hi> being for that his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had been, ſo friendly and effectuall a meanes for relieving <hi>Crosbies</hi> brother, when beſieged with the Rebels in the Fort of <hi>Ballingary</hi> at ſeverall times.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>To the ſixth.</head>
               <p n="5">5 That <hi>Lambard</hi> being an inhabitant in the City of <hi>Corke</hi> never acted any thing to the prejudice of the Parliament, but on the contrary did give the Lord Preſident intelligence, and Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ill affection born unto the Engliſh Army by many of the inhabitants of that town, and of their practice and combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114473:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>with ſome of the Rebels abroad in that County, whereupon he was at the expulſion of the Iriſh (among ſome few others that have done ſervice in the ſame kind) promiſed by the Lord Preſident that he ſhould enjoy the benefit of his Eſtate, in and about the City whilſt he lived in our Quarters, which he accordingly did receive by his Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes) whereof one of them might be the Lord Preſident Steward for ought he knew) after his removall towards the County of <hi>Limrick</hi> he did give the Lord Preſident advertiſement of what he would leave a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Rebels to the advantage of the ſervice, which when he ceaſed to do whereby the Lord Preſident apprehended he was joyned with the Rebels, his Lordſhip gave order that ſtay ſhould be made of the profits of his eſtate, and that they ſhould be converted to the uſe of the Army.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>To the Seventh.</head>
               <p n="7">7 That <hi>Fitz Patrick</hi> pretending ſome negotiation, that might much conduce to the good of the Parliaments Army, was admitted by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Councell into the Gariſon of <hi>Cork,</hi> where he made an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from <hi>Owen Ree Oneal,</hi> on the behalf of the Popes <hi>Nuntio,</hi> That the Lord Preſident would ſtand Newtrall, and ſuffer them that were of the <hi>Nuntio's</hi> party to diſpute their differences with thoſe that adhered to the peace, with the Lord of <hi>Ormond</hi> by the ſword, uſed arguments to perſwade the Preſident not to incline to <hi>Ormonds</hi> party, for that he and all the <hi>Butlers</hi> had ever hated the Lord Preſidents family with much diſcourſe to that purpoſe, whereunto the Lord Preſident and Councell gave ſuch anſwer, as they conceived would tend moſt to the aggravation of thoſe differences betwixt the Rebels, and yet keep them free from ingagement towards them, And of this proceeding, the Lord Preſident did give an account by Letter to the Lord Lieutenant or Committee of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and therefore it is a ſtrange proceeding in the L. of <hi>Broghill</hi> and Sir <hi>Arthur Loftus</hi> (who could not be ignorant there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) to charge this as a fault on the Preſident: After this about the ſpace of a Moneth, and after it had been long debated at the Councell and that Sir <hi>Piercy Smith,</hi> and Lieutenant Colonell <hi>Cook</hi> had been nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to go and deſired to be excuſed, Captain <hi>Alexander Pigoe,</hi> whoſe father and family had no obligation to the Earl of <hi>Ormond</hi> was by his own deſire (having newly heard of the death of his father) ſent to <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> with Letters to the Commiſſioners appointed by the Parliament, there to treat, and to the Lord <hi>Ormond</hi> with an anſwer to a Letter he received from him, which was ſent to the Lord Preſident by Captaine
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114473:9"/>
                  <hi>Willoughby</hi> cheife Commander of the Parliament Ships then there, wherein the Lord of <hi>Ormond</hi> declared to the Preſident his intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſtand for the Parliament, and did deſire his aſſiſtance. But upon Captaine <hi>Pigots</hi> comming to the Bay of <hi>Dublin</hi> he found the Commiſſioners (not as in the Article is mentioned at the Harbours mouth) to be gone the day before, whereupon he communicated his directions and inſtructions to the Commanders at Sea, Captaine <hi>Willoughby,</hi> Captaine <hi>Moulton</hi> and ſuch others as were there, who did adviſe, give way to, and approve of his going into <hi>Dublin</hi> to ſee his diſconſolate Mother and Siſters, and ſent to <hi>Dublin</hi> for a paſſe for him, And thereupon his Letters to the Lord of <hi>Ormond</hi> and his inſtructions he left in Captaine <hi>Willoughbyes</hi> hands leaſt he ſhould be ſearcht, his inſtructions being to communicate his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the Lord of <hi>Ormond</hi> firſt with the Commiſſioners of the Parliament and all that he had in charge to negotiate with <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> being that he would ſend ſome Agent into <hi>Munſter</hi> with pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate directions, to ſome that commanded ſeverall places of ſtrength in the Rebells quarters, (and were likely to comply with his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip) to deliver up their Commands to the Parliaments Army, upon ſignification of his intention unto them, as alſo that his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip would cauſe the Sword and other Enſignes of the Majorality (which the late Major of <hi>Corke</hi> ſtole away and preſented to his Lordſhip) to be ſent downe. But Captaine <hi>Pigot</hi> did not conferre with the Lord of <hi>Ormond</hi> about any thing, as he is ready to depoſe being now in this City, and that the maine cauſe which drew him thither, was to relieve and viſit his diſtreſſed Mother, and Siſters who were ſent to that Towne ſtripped by the Rebells even to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, being thirteene in family, and his Father holding out a Caſtle of great importance againſt the Rebells, called <hi>Diſert</hi> in the Queenes County then lately was betrayed and ſurprized, and in the moſt inhumane manner that hath been heard of murthered and his body caſt forth into a ditch, his ſonne, his Chaplyn and moſt of his men with him to the number of 42. being alſo fouly butchered in the preſence of his Mother who with her daughters were ſtript, and barbarouſly by them driven through the fire. The Gentleman and his Father Sir <hi>Robert Pigot</hi> having been perſons of faire eſtates, and the greateſt eminency for their zeale and affection to Religion that their times and thoſe parts did produce as is generally known
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114473:9"/>to all the well affected thereabouts. And cannot be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to Sir <hi>Arthur Loftus</hi> being Cozen Iermaine to the ſaid diſtreſſed wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow now in this City.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>To the eight.</head>
               <p n="8">8. The words ſuppoſed to be ſpoken to Collonel <hi>Polland.</hi> The Lord Preſident doth in the firſt place deny to have uttered any word to that ſenſe, whereunto they are wreſted to the ſaid Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, who denyeth that he ever heard the ſaid Lord Preſident uſe any words to that effect, or that the ſaid Collonel ever reported them to any perſon whatſoever from the Lord Preſident, in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and forme, and in the ſenſe as they are charged in the ſaid Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, which may the more probably receive credit in reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d his Lordſhips practice hath bin utterly repugnant thereunto, in the tranſaction of all his buſineſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>To the ninth.</head>
               <p n="9">9. The abuſes in the ſtore charged to be committed by his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is a notoricus ſcandall, and ſo knowne both to the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>latou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and the Lord of <hi>Broghill</hi> himſelfe, hath with the reſt of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers in generall by an Inſtrument dated the firſt of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, vindicated the Lord Preſident from it to which vindication this Article may juſtly be referred for an anſwer, And this charge is indeed a moſt injurious Calumny for that the Preſident hath been ever moſt carefull, and tender to prevent any abuſe in that kind, and hereof the Clearke of the Store, and Commiſſary of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazine would be beſt able to acquit or accuſe his Lordſhip. In the meane time it will appeare that the Lord Preſident hath out of his owne purſe and proviſions, and out of his Mothers and Friends ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the ſtores when greatly exhauſted, and when heavy Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances and deepe danger would have riſen to the States Intereſt if his Lordſhip had not uſed his diligence Induſtry and Credit to prevent them as is well knowne even to the relators themſelves, and as it hath been already by the ſaid Inſtrument, ſo will bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine cleerely atteſted, And on the cloſe of all accompts will be fully evidenced.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <head>To the tenth.</head>
               <p n="10">10 That ſome Prieſts have been included within the Articles of Contribution within the Country (without which the Country, would never have ſubmitted, and without which the Army could not have ſubſiſted) is confeſſed. But that Souldiers ſupreame Councell men or men of the generall aſſembly were protected being in Command or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114473:10"/>known to be of the ſupreame Councell is not ſo, for Souldiers none were protected but upon the generall Articles of Contribution, that is to lay down Arms &amp;c. which was done out of a conſiderable regard to take off as many as was poſſible from the ſtronger part of the Rebels which was held to be that of the <hi>Nuntio's,</hi> and to ballance their Forces ſo that one part might not be able to ſuppreſſe the other readily, but that the differences might be upheld, wherein our ſafety (before the Forces arrived) did for a long time conſiſt. But moreover our own quarters were thereby much improved and inhabited, the Rebells impaired, our markets the more plentifully repleniſhed, and at eaſier rates, and our Contribution made more conſiderable and certain, and more punctual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paid. For men of the ſupreame Councell it is denied that ever any of them were protected, being ſo, and known to be ſo. It might fall out, that when the late ſupreame Councell was ſupplanted and ſuppreſſed, and a new one erected there might ſome of the old have protections for their Tenants and Cattell, as ſome that were formerly under contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution might be choſen of the new, which can in no reaſonable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction reflect on the Preſident. For thoſe of the generall aſſembly, it is ſaid that when the diviſions grew happily to ſo great height that there was violent ſiding on either party. The Lord Preſident and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell did eſteem it neither ill policy nor ill ſervice as their condition was then) to increaſe and uphold thoſe differences all they could, and to that end being ſought unto by ſome perſons of the country, that were to be of their Nationall aſſembly did encourage and ingage them to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the predominant party amongſt the ſaid Rebels at <hi>Kilkenny</hi> and did let fall words which might incourage them to hope that they would deſend them againſt the adverſe party, and for this end and to gain intelligence of the Rebels proceedings, and tranſactions the L. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident did protect ſome (but none ſave thoſe formerly under contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) that went to the Generall aſſembly with the privity of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and by that means had frequent advertiſements thence, and did thereby undoubtedly contribute ſo much to the aggravation of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferencies, as that 3 ſeverall times they fell to blows with their drawne ſwords in their great convention which probably had not determined there, if the interpoſition of their Friars and Clergy, and the Lord of <hi>Ormonds</hi> unexpected offer of the the ſurrender of <hi>Dublin</hi> have not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred to allay their heats one towards another, and make them entire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <head>To the eleventh.</head>
               <p n="11">11 That Maſſe hath been ſaid pubickly in <hi>Cork</hi> or <hi>Kingſale</hi> fithence the L. Preſidents Commiſſion, and with his privity, alowance or conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance is denied.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:114473:10"/>
               <head>To the twelfth.</head>
               <p n="12">12 That the Lord Preſident might ſend a meſſage, or intend one in the nature of a ſummons to the Caſtle of <hi>Ballimarter,</hi> is but agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to al proceedings military in like caſes, and that the Caſtle of <hi>Bali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marter,</hi> was commanded by a Friar or Prieſt is poſſible, or that the L. Preſident might think of ſending ſuch a meſſage, the more to afright or terrifie the reſt of the Defendants (having hanged a Prieſt, but at the laſt Caſtle he took before) or the more to facilitate the delivery up of the place, by the reſt that ſhould remain if the Prieſts (who had power over their conſciences) were gone is not improbable. But that his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, did the ſame, in favour of their Clergy, or in a deſire to preſerve them, is a moſt injurious Inſinuation, His Lordſhip having hanged a prieſt (with them a famous Deane] at the laſt Caſtle he took as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, lying near <hi>Ballimarter.</hi> That he hanged alſo one of their titular Deans at <hi>Bandon Br.</hi> and the double hanging of Friar <hi>Francis Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thews,</hi> a great Provinciall Factor for the Pope, and highly eſteemed, and his death mightily reſented by the Queen will teſtify his little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to their Clergy, which being reall truths will merit greater cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and conſideration, then to admit of what would be inforced on this ſuggeſtion, as for <hi>Edmund Fitz Gerald,</hi> who is a notorious rebell, and uncle to the L. Preſident by half blood, if his relation had been nearer it will contrary to the intent of the Relaters, much aſſert the Lord Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents integrity in that he made choyce of firſt of all to fall into the country which belonged to a perſon ſo near unto him of kin, where he firſt took his eldeſt ſons Caſtle, and afterwards his own, which he blew up with powder, and demoliſhed it as near as he could, ſtaying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in perſon to ſee it done, till the Rebells Army were advanced over the black water to relieve that place, and drawn within leſſe then two miles of it, being onely hindered and delayed in their march by our Horſe facing theirs, and forcing them to two ſeverall ſtands til their foot drew up to them, And if this <hi>Fitz Gerald</hi> had been his father, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying of his country, excepting him out of all benefit of quarter, when that Country did afterwards ſubmit to Contribution will mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt as little favour towards that Rebellious bloudy faction, as theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles hold forth either of juſtice or conſcientiouſneſſe, when theſe things are urged againſt his Lordſhip as crimes which are known to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators to be highly conducing to the States ſervice.</p>
               <p>And to the end the matter of protections might be rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood it being alleaged that the L. Preſident did grant them out of his affection to the Iriſh, which is the more likely to gaine credit
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114473:11"/>becauſe he is that Countryman by birth, It will appear that nothing but extreame neceſſitie did occaſion his granting of them, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that courſe had been taken the Parliaments, intereſt then could not have been preſerved, that he granted them not without adviſe and conſent of the Counſell whoſe adviſe and direction he hath been directed by the Parliament to follow, and that he uſed ſuch caution therein that it was expreſly conditioned that each Inhabitant who tooke any protection ſhould lay down Armes, the advantages and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of which courſe may abundantly ſatisfy all men that are not prepoſſeſſed with paſſion or prejudice, &amp; beſides this courſe was the ſame which for great and weighty reaſons and conſiderations hath uſually been taken by ſuch as have been imployed by authority of this preſent Parliament, as fit to be continued till they may convenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſupply the Army, in ſuch manner as they may not be neceſſitated to admit of protected Rebells to contribution and to markets for a ſubſiſtance, and if any man be yet unſatisfied, they may be pleaſed to take a view of an inſtruction given to the Commiſſioners of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, imployed to the Lord of <hi>Ormond</hi> in <hi>Nov.</hi> 1646. Appearing in the booke of treaty with his Lordſhip <hi>pag.</hi> 55. <hi>viz.</hi> you or any 3. of you have power hereby to give protection to ſuch as will come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der contribution and to give them the beſt fafeguard you can by the countenance of the forces ſerving under the Parliament, And in their explanation of their inſtructions in <hi>pag.</hi> 32. paragr. 3. it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed that power is given (as by the ſaid Inſtructions of the 16. of <hi>Nov.</hi>) to protect ſuch as will come under contribution and to give them ſafe guard by the countenance of the forces ſerving under the Parliament, according to which they are to be protected in their perſons and eſtates aſwell from the violence of the Souldiers under the Parliament as of the enemy, And this to be extended to all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſtinction of offence or Religion, This was offered by the late Commiſſioners to the Lord of <hi>Ormond</hi> and afterwards all their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers upon his Lordſhips laſt overture, were approved by Order of both Houſes of Parliament dated 22. <hi>Feb.</hi> 1646. And the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners had particular inſtructions to make them good, as by their Proclamation dated 23. of <hi>Iune</hi> laſt did publiſh, ſo as no man can juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tax the ſaid Lord Preſident with favouring the Iriſh in this his proceeding tending ſo much to the Parliaments ſervice, in preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their intereſt and the lives of many thouſand poore Proteſtants who have loſt their fortunes for their ſakes.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Rich. Gathing</hi> Secretary.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
